<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Otic reprogramming</title>
 <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/"/>
 <updated>2021-01-04T12:05:39-06:00</updated>
 <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Alex Thiery</name>
   <email>alexthiery1@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>The key to early diagnosis in Autism&#58; three research areas</title>
   <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2014/02/17/ASD-research-short/"/>
   <updated>2014-02-17T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2014/02/17/ASD-research-short</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I’m hoping they will realize they get better bang for their buck, the earlier intervention is given.”&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a title=&quot;Toronto Star February 2013&quot; href=&quot;http://www.thestar.com/news/canada/2013/02/08/ontarios_auditor_general_to_review_autism_services.html&quot;&gt;said Simone Papernick of Whitby&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ontario Auditor General just initiated a review of Autism Services to better determine how to spend the recently tripled budget for treatment. The budget now stands at $186 million a year for Ontarian’s with the developmental disorder. Demand has never been higher, Autism is now estimated to affect 1 in 88 children, based on reports from the Centre For Disease Control in the United States. However, one of the best solutions to making treatment more effective is earlier diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diagnosing children at an earlier age means earlier intervention at a time when the child’s brain is changing rapidly and has the potential to be influenced by life experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently the best therapy for young children with Autism is Intensive Behavioural Intervention (IBI), which uses a comprehensive approach to support a child’s healthy development. This therapy costs as much as $60,000 a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To improve the effectiveness of IBI, three early interventions hold strong potential. The first is the understanding of genetic factors which contribute to increased risk in developing Autism. The second is understanding how children who go on to develop autism have subtle differences in behaviour from children who don’t develop the disorder. Thirdly, using imaging brain during development to understand how the brain may grow differently in children who go on to be diagnosed with Autism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to seeing all three grow over time and tell us more about the brain’s intricacies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further information:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The Hospital for Sick Children's Stephen Scherer on TVO's the agenda: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tbUFMf2hHKU&quot;&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tbUFMf2hHKU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The genetic landscapes of autism spectrum disorders by Huguet G, Ey E, Bourgeron T. (2013) - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23875794&quot;&gt;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23875794&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A Comparison of Neuroimaging Findings in Childhood Onset Schizophrenia and Autism Spectrum Disorder: A Review of the Literature by Baribeau DA, Anagnostou E. (2013) - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24391605&quot;&gt;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24391605&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Translational approaches to the biology of Autism: false dawn or a new era? by Ecker C, Spooren W, Murphy DG. (2013) - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22801412&quot;&gt;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22801412&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Baby Sib study - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.autismspeaks.org/science/research-initiatives/high-risk-baby-sibs&quot;&gt;http://www.autismspeaks.org/science/research-initiatives/high-risk-baby-sibs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Autism research, traversing the full spectrum to help children</title>
   <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2013/01/19/autism-oped/"/>
   <updated>2013-01-19T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2013/01/19/autism-oped</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With a prevalence of one in 88 children, autism has moved to the forefront of discussions amongst Canadian parents. To propel this discussion from the kitchen table to the greater community, the Toronto Star produced a useful series entitled the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thestar.com/news/world/autismproject&quot; title=&quot;Autism Project&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Autism Project&lt;/a&gt;. Yet, little has been discussed on how research is describing brain dysfunction in autism and developing treatments to correct this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To recap first: autism, as medicine currently defines it, is a disorder where the brain’s processing of information is affected, disrupting communication, sociability and other behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Star’s series examined the personal experience of autism from the perspectives of a parent and individuals with the disorder. It highlighted new behavioural therapies, the work being done to study the genetics of autism patients, and the frustrating wait many parents face in getting their child access to behavioural interventions. However, the series missed how research on the biology of autism is translating our knowledge of genetics into new treatments. This matters because this research contains the potential to improve lives and lessen autism’s impact on society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The brain in autism processes information differently and understanding the details of the process will help facilitate research on new treatments. The federal government recognizes this and has just committed $1-million to funding a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cihr-irsc.gc.ca/e/46009.html&quot; title=&quot;CIHR announcement&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Canadian research chair&lt;/a&gt; for 5 years to accelerate Canada’s contribution to finding new treatments. This represents a good start to advancing Canadian research on autism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canada’s science contribution is accelerating as well. Researchers, as part of an international project, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ontariogenomics.ca/research/project/44&quot; title=&quot;Scherer Screening&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;screened over 6000 people with autism&lt;/a&gt; to understand the disorder’s genetic factors. This and other work showed that many genetic pieces contribute to the scientific puzzle of autism. Using these genetic factors, a careful examination of the brain’s biological dysfunction in autism can be done to develop new treatments. This includes unraveling changes in brain function, development and structure associated with each genetic piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small success story has come with a specific gene that causes Fragile X syndrome, a disorder closely related to autism. Researchers first laid a foundation for developing treatments by characterizing the Fragile X gene’s effect on brain function and structure. Then, earlier this year, a team at Massachusetts Institute of Technology used this knowledge to &lt;a href=&quot;http://stm.sciencemag.org/content/4/152/152ra128.abstract&quot; title=&quot;FXS Reversal&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;reverse the syndrome’s deficits&lt;/a&gt;. They corrected brain abnormalities in a model of Fragile X syndrome and &lt;a href=&quot;http://stm.sciencemag.org/content/4/152/152ra127&quot; title=&quot;FXS phase 2 trial article&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;improved social engagement in Fragile X patients&lt;/a&gt;, all with the same treatment. This case illustrates why establishing new treatments through an understanding of the brain in autism matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fragile X story is just one piece of the puzzle and many more pieces contribute to autism. To continue progress, knowledge on how genetics change brain function and structure in autism must press on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, almost every month this body of knowledge grows. Since 2011 several models of genetic traits in autism have had biological and behaviour problems reversed using targeted treatments. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed?term=Autism-related%20deficits%20via%20dysregulated%20eIF4E-dependent%20translational%20control&quot; title=&quot;McGill Autism&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this month researchers at McGill University&lt;/a&gt; announced successful correction of behaviour and biological shortfalls in a new genetic model of autism. Though this work is not ready for humans, it does strengthen the foundation on what exactly is going awry in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These frequent advances help build an understanding of the biological pathways affected in autism and some successful ways to therapeutically target the brain for treating the disorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the mountain to climb in autism research remains high, great gains have been made. We now know that the genetic contribution to autism is strong and that many different genetic factors cause the disorder. Discussions on autism now must include new research focused on deciphering the disorder’s biological riddle. Solving this enables science to translate its genetic knowledge to better treatments for individuals with autism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going forward, the key to further success will be translating the genetic factors to treatments that improve the lives of children and adults with autism. Furthermore, more genetic models will need to be investigated to form a comprehensive picture of autism and in deciding which targeted treatments to use. Only further support from the government and public in funding autism research can empower scientists to answer these remaining questions.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>