<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Patrick Steadman</title>
 <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/"/>
 <updated>2021-01-04T06:31:22-06:00</updated>
 <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Patrick Steadman</name>
   <email>patrick.steadman[at]mail[dot]utoronto[dot]ca</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Updated ruby on OS X 12 using HomeBrew</title>
   <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2017/11/29/updating-website-ruby/"/>
   <updated>2017-11-29T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2017/11/29/updating-website-ruby</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My old Gemfile.lock had a dependency with a known DoS vulnerability and Github notified me to fix. This ran into some issues of OS X 12 install of ruby (v 2.0.0) so I decided to switch over to HomeBrew and manage my own ruby env there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;setup&quot;&gt;Setup&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Install HomeBrew:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ruby -e &quot;$(curl -fsSL https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Homebrew/install/master/install)&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now set up with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rbenv&lt;/code&gt; to manage different ruby install versions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-sh highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;brew update &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; brew upgrade
brew doctor

brew &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;install &lt;/span&gt;rbenv
brew &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;install &lt;/span&gt;ruby-build
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'export RBENV_ROOT=/usr/local/var/rbenv'&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; ~/.bash_profile
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'if which rbenv &amp;gt; /dev/null; then eval &quot;$(rbenv init -)&quot;; fi'&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; ~/.bash_profile

rbenv &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;install&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-l&lt;/span&gt;
rbenv &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;install &lt;/span&gt;2.4.0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open a new terminal and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rbenv shell 2.4.0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check this has all completed correctly with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rbenv versions&lt;/code&gt; should show OS X v of 2.0.0 and my installed version of 2.4.0. Then check with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ruby --version&lt;/code&gt; now that I have set the global for this bash session to 2.4.0 and it should return that as the version. Can also check the ruby location with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;which ruby&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then install bundler with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gem install bundler&lt;/code&gt;
Then install jekyll with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gem install jekyll&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once this was completed I changed to my github pages directory in my terminal session. Then I used bundle to check my Gemfile and install the dependencies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-sh highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;bundle
bundle &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;install&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That updated my Gemfile.lock to the latest versions of dependcies for Github pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;ongoing-maintenance&quot;&gt;Ongoing maintenance&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To move from the system to another ruby version per shell session start with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rbenv shell 2.4.0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then run&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bundle exec jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Algorithms and Learning</title>
   <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2017/11/16/learning-circuits/"/>
   <updated>2017-11-16T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2017/11/16/learning-circuits</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The last few days at SfN came at me, and maybe you, from all angles. It has been a deluge of information and insight into some amazing work. One ‘theme’ covered the mechanisms of learning from both biological and computational perspectives. Lets take a look at presentations from both vantages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presenting in the session ‘From salient experience to learning and memory’, Dr. Andreas Lüthi examined how an association between a conditioned stimulus (CS) and an unconditioned stimulus (US) is formed by amygdalar neuronal circuits. Understanding the process of forming associations may help prevent or treat anxiety disorders, where a stimulus that may not be concerning is causing debilitating anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Principal cells in the Basolateral region of the amygdala rarely fire. Lüthi believes strong inhibition from surrounding interneurons limit principal cells from firing. They visualized the activity of interneurons during an associative learning task to understand the role of inhibition. These experiments found that VIP interneurons initially respond to the unconditioned stimulus and that subsequent unconditioned stimuli cause a decrease in VIP cell activity. This decrease in inhibitory signal correlates with an increasing in freezing, a common behavioral output measure. They also found that inhibiting VIP activity during associative learning reduced freezing during memory retrieval later. Therefore to properly form the association VIP interneurons need to fire initially to facilitate the formation of increased activity in the principal neurons, then decrease in firing to allow the principal neurons to help trigger the behavioral output through circuits projecting from the amygdala.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving more broadly, general computational methods for learning are being investigated at Google’s DeepMind, run by Dr. Demis Hassabis. During a lecture he examined the recent interplay between neuroscience and artificial intelligence. As an aside, I was happy to see in Dr. Demis Hassabis’s thesis a chapter on Engrams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2017-11-16_Hassabis_thesis.png&quot; alt=&quot;Hassabis Engrams, 80%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work at DeepMind has trained neural networks on the game Go, and others, to beat human champions. The learning of difficult games to such an extreme level has taught Go players new strategies and Hassabis argues this level of learning will broaden our collective intelligence rather than undermine human capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The company has additionally started to develop neural networks that when given 2-3 2D views of an environment can generate the entire 3D space. Right now this works for simplistic spaces but the ability to generate scene’s he hopes will teach us about our own ability to imagine. And together these computer algorithms will inform us about the human experience of learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two lectures explored learning but in very different ways. The biological approach informs us on our natural algorithms and their circuitry. The computational explores learning tasks we do naturally but with circuitry which may not reflect biology. From this we can compare and contrast. Even more interesting is that the computational learning algorithms are able to advance our knowledge, as observed in the strategies with Go. This perhaps navigates us around circuit ‘blocks’ in our own learning systems to a better understanding of the natural world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick E. Steadman, MSc&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;PhD Candidate, Frankland Lab, The Hospital for Sick Children&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;MD-PhD Student, University of Toronto&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Neuronline: @patrick.steadman&lt;br /&gt;
Twitter: &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/pesteadman&quot;&gt;@pesteadman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Blog: &lt;a href=&quot;http://patricksteadman.ca/blog&quot;&gt;patricksteadman.ca/blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Beyond Place Cells</title>
   <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2017/11/13/beyond-place-cells/"/>
   <updated>2017-11-13T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2017/11/13/beyond-place-cells</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thanks to O’Keefe and Dostrovsky 45 years ago place cells were discovered in the hippocampus. Since then people have been studying the neurophysiology of neurons to see how place, among other features of the world around us are coded. In this #SfN17 session presenters were urged to move ‘Beyond place cells’ and thankfully many have been doing just that for a number of years. However, many questions remain about mechanistically how the hippocampus and associated structures process for coding environmental features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.frontline.in/multimedia/dynamic/02171/fl14_nobel_medicin_2171449g.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Coding cells, 25%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source: http://www.frontline.in/multimedia/dynamic/02171/fl14_nobel_medicin_2171449g.jpg&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were many highlights from this session which featured many exceptional neuroscientists including Drs Carolyn Barnes, Nachum Ulanovsky, Edvard Moser, Mayank Mehta, Jeffery Magee, and Dmitriy Aranov. A few of those highlights are covered below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Barnes, whose maze was the first behavioral apparatus I used, has been a champion of translating information learned about place cells from rats to higher order species, in particular monkeys. This is important to show what learned in rodents translates to humans. Dr. Barnes and her lab utilized a method for assessing cellular plasticity markers known as Arc catFISH. The method was employed following real or virual space exploration and examined expression in the dentate gyrus (DG), CA1 and CA3 regions of the hippocampus. All three regions had increased levels of Arc for real and virtual exploration compared to control monkeys, however only the CA1 region was elevated for the real exploration over virtual. A similar result had been shown previously in rats, a win for scientific findings in one species holding for others. The data next revealed that the proportion of CA1 neurons active in the real exploration as a total of all CA1 neurons was three times lower in the monkey than in the rat. One interpretation is that the monkey may be able to code for more space than the rat. This has yet to be tested explicitly, but would prove informative as the spaces both species utilize experimentally are small relative to real-world environments they traverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Ulanovsky was second and his work in bats moves from small spaces to larger ones more naturalistic to see how place cells and other cell types function. One of his experiments recorded neurons as bats flew down a long 200 m tunnel. He found single neurons to code for several ‘places’ along the tunnel. Further neurons could code for a small meters wide segment of the tunnel and large segments 10s of meters long. Perhaps this is more naturalistically how place cells work in our CA1 as we navigate the conference centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When moving through space we are often guided by goals (e.g. coffee). Dr. Ulanovsky has also examined how hippocampal cells code for spatial goals. This work, published in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.weizmann.ac.il/neurobiology/labs/ulanovsky/sites/neurobiology.labs.ulanovsky/files/uploads/sarel_etal_science2017.pdf&quot;&gt;2017 in Science&lt;/a&gt;, found in 3D space neurons can code for vectors towards goals including the vectors length as well as angle. This is coded by firing when the goal is a specific angle (theta in the figure below) to the bat. Further the firing rate for these cells increased as the bat approached the goal along the vector (angle) thus coding for vector angle and length. Two features in one neuron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2017-11-13_spatial_goal_vectors_v2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Vector goals, 50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many have posited that this codifying of space in the hippocampus and associated structures (i.e. medial entorhinal cortex, MEC) is not just a means of representing physical features but more generally any set of features. Dr. Aronov presented work examining this by creating a tasking using auditory cues, more specifically sound frequency, tied to a reward. This task therefore did not rely on spatial features. Rodents had to hold a lever down which triggered a sound to increase in frequency and to release the lever during a specific frequency window to receive a reward. By recording CA1 cells he found they coded for specific frequencies, even if the rate of frequency climb was changed to ensure it was not a coding of time. He was also able to identify cells in the MEC that coded for elements of the auditory task as well. If this sounds interesting, check his paper out in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/nature21692.epdf&quot;&gt;Nature&lt;/a&gt; from earlier this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An exceptional session showing we are still learning much about how the hippocampus and MEC code space as well as how these structures code for other features of our environment. Fascinating!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick E. Steadman, MSc&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;PhD Candidate, Frankland Lab, The Hospital for Sick Children&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;MD-PhD Student, University of Toronto&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Neuronline: @patrick.steadman&lt;br /&gt;
Twitter: &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/pesteadman&quot;&gt;@pesteadman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Blog: &lt;a href=&quot;http://patricksteadman.ca/blog&quot;&gt;patricksteadman.ca/blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Myelin in the early and late stages of life</title>
   <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2017/11/11/myelin-early-and-late/"/>
   <updated>2017-11-11T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2017/11/11/myelin-early-and-late</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-could-sleep-aging-and-myelin-be-related&quot;&gt;How could sleep, aging and myelin be related?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes its good to get out of your wheelhouse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://smart.servier.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/Neurone012-361x680.png&quot; alt=&quot;SMART Neuron with myelin, 5%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two posters presented today explored myelin modifications at different life stages. In the first, the effect of chronic sleep loss during adolescence was found to decrease the thickness of myelin in the Corpus Callosum and the Lateral Olfactory Tract. Adolescence is a key time for myelin development which continues in the human brain until our late 20’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This poster made me wonder what I did to my brain during those late nights I spent playing video games during my own adolescence?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is interesting about this finding on myelin in chronic sleep loss is that previous work showed sleep loss suppressed myelin-related genes. Suggesting at a molecular level an importance for sleep in myelin maintenance. Next steps should better characterize this relationship and how it may relate to  adolescent development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://a.scpr.org/i/cb4c973a1f235907055ac7229772d842/159835-full.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sleepy, 5%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second poster moved from me the young brain to the aged brain. This poster examined ERK1/2 activation in oligodendrocytes, which had previously been shown to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3711773/&quot;&gt;enhance myelination&lt;/a&gt;. The role of ERK1/2 has been studied before at a molecular signaling level, so connecting this to cellular and behavioral function can help integrate our understanding of brain function. Further, as we age brain function decreases including affecting memory. Would sustained activation of ERK1/2 in oligodendrocytes affect cognitive decline? From a young age, mice had oligodendrocytes trigger sustained ERK1/2 signalling which persisted as long as the oligodendrocyte lived. Behaviorally this led to an increase in contextual fear memory in aged mice only. However, it remains unclear how to interpret this finding. Perhaps over time some oligodendrocytes die with aging, and it could be that those with sustained ERK1/2 activation survive longer. Therefore in old mice with their persisting ERK1/2 activation oligodendrocytes, these cells could help facilitate this behaviour. This work is preliminary and needs additional experiments to explore this interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both these posters introduced me to new concepts on the shared topic of white matter in the brain. I can’t wait to see what new info tomorrow brings!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick E. Steadman, MSc&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;PhD Candidate, Frankland Lab, The Hospital for Sick Children&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;MD-PhD Student, University of Toronto&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Neuronline: @patrick.steadman&lt;br /&gt;
Twitter: &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/pesteadman&quot;&gt;@pesteadman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Blog: &lt;a href=&quot;http://patricksteadman.ca/blog&quot;&gt;patricksteadman.ca/blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Blogging at SfN 2017</title>
   <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2017/10/25/SfNBloggerIntro/"/>
   <updated>2017-10-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2017/10/25/SfNBloggerIntro</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi! I am one of the 2017 Society for Neuroscience Bloggers. I will be posting at Neuronline under the official bloggers tags and at &lt;a href=&quot;http://patricksteadman.ca/blog&quot;&gt;my website&lt;/a&gt;. I will be writing about these two themes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;G - Motivation and Emotion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;H - Cognition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.gravatar.com/avatar/3a91811708b61787ecd9018c9becc99b?s=240&quot; alt=&quot;Patrick&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My background is in learning and memory, neuroimaging and computer analysis. I am interested in writing about engrams, neuronal circuits in neuropsychiatric disorders and how we are uncovering them using new techniques, and lastly the relationship between neuroscience and artificial intelligence. I’m in particular hoping to chat with graduate students and post-docs, getting their perspective and profiling their contributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you in November!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick E. Steadman, MSc&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;PhD Candidate, Frankland Lab, The Hospital for Sick Children&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;MD-PhD Student, University of Toronto&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Neuronline: @patrick.steadman&lt;br /&gt;
Twitter: &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/pesteadman&quot;&gt;@pesteadman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Blog: &lt;a href=&quot;http://patricksteadman.ca/blog&quot;&gt;patricksteadman.ca/blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Are physicians good advocates?</title>
   <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2015/01/09/aredocsgoodadvocates/"/>
   <updated>2015-01-09T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2015/01/09/aredocsgoodadvocates</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;During my training last year as a medical student a great emphasis was placed on interprofessional education. I learnt about the other health professionals and the vital roles they play in providing the best care for patients. Some of the other professionals appeared to me to be very well suited for patient advocacy. It made me wonder what makes physicians suited for patient advocacy and population health advocacy. I decided to see what literature there was on this topic…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, what makes a physician positioned so well for health advocacy work? According to the literature, they “understand the medical aspects of issues better than any sector of society, and they are poised to observe and delineate the links between social factors and health” (Earnest et al. 2010). Furthermore, they are highly trusted by the public for information related to health. Unfortunately, some research shows physicians are more likely to engage in issues affecting their own economic well-being rather than those benefiting society as a whole (Grumbach et al. 1998 NEJM). Given the great potential physicians have for advocacy work, but the (somewhat dated) evidence for them to mostly act in their own best interest, wouldn’t it be wonderful to train physicians to ensure they serve as ‘good’ advocates? As in primarily advocating for improved health in their communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well then what do advocates need in their toolbox for such work. They need to be positioned to identify a problem, be able to define it and its scope, know who to engage in strategizing a solution and be able to communicate effectively to the necessary decision-makers (Earnest et al. 2010). Physicians along with other health professionals are positioned to answer all those questions for health advocacy. And even when the physician cannot perfectly realize the scope of a problem, given the inter-professional team-oriented nature of their work, they can seek others out collaboratively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then how can we ensure the problems they identify to solve will better their community’s health? Earnest et al. (2010) and a reply by Dworkis et al. (2010) state that a fundamental understanding of the determinants of health followed by practical experience in advocacy projects are important to developing physicians into health advocates. Getting experience in these early in medical training is essential then. This then brings us from the evidence that physicians can be good advocates to how do we ensure they are through medical education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Learning objectives dealing with advocacy theory might include (1) formally identifying and distinguishing between the roles that physicians must, should, and could perform within the spectrum of physician advocacy, and (2) developing a rigorous understanding of the social determinants of health.” - Dworkis (2010)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily such training and experience aligns with our superiors intentions in training new physicians. In a 2001 report, titled &lt;em&gt;Social Accountability: A Vision for Canadian Medical Schools&lt;/em&gt;, we see that a “primary goal of medical education is to prepare graduates to practice effectively in reducing the burden of illness and improving the health of their communities.” (Health canada, 2011)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is great, right? Well another editorial in 2011 as well (must’ve been a busy year for this) makes a different argument in training physician advocates. Kanter’s (2011) editorial considers, based on previous compelling papers, whether all physicians should become advocates. The argument against is for the fear of politicizing all physician efforts as advocacy and it being equated to political advocacy. A question remains then, do efforts for healthier public policy necessarily require politicking?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it isn’t so much as seeing health advocacy as a battle in politics but rather as framing health advocacy as an act of social accountability that physicians are held to. Meaning society expects physicians to work for the best care of all Canadians in an equitable and just manner. This statement I believe transends political lines and is really what health advocacy is about. Such a view should not be lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidence therefore suggests physicians can be positioned well as advocates for healthcare, and that this emphasis on advocacy can be instilled in medical education. And lastly, I believe health advocacy != political advocacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A photo of a medical student advocacy campaign to increase the number of Ontarians registered as organ donors; truly good advocacy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2015-01-09_GiftOfLifeUofT_tweet.png?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Medical student campaign to increase the number of Ontarians registered as organ donors&quot; /&gt;
Source: &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/UofTGoL/status/426465189962084352&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;REFERENCES:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Dworkis, Daniel A., MaryAnn B. Wilbur, and Megan T. Sandel. “A framework for designing training in medical advocacy.” Academic Medicine 85.10 (2010): 1549-1550.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Earnest MA, Wong SL, Federico SG. Perspective: Physician advocacy: What is it and how do we do it? Acad Med. 2010;85:63–67.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Grumbach K, Osmond D, Vranizan K, Jaffe D, Bindman AB. Primary care physicians’ experience of financial incentives in managed-care systems. N Engl J Med. 1998; 339:1516 –1521.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Kanter, Steven L. “On Physician Advocacy.” Academic Medicine 86.9 (2011): 1059-1060.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Social Accountability: A Vision for Canadian Medical Schools. Health Canada, 2011. &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;https://www.afmc.ca/pdf/pdf_sa_vision_canadian_medical_schools_en.pdf&lt;/a&gt;. Accessed November 14, 2014
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>On medical students becoming health advocates</title>
   <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2014/12/05/trainingphysicianadvocates/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-05T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2014/12/05/trainingphysicianadvocates</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A patient is unable to afford medications necessary to manage their chronic illness. As a physician, you may not even inquire as to whether the patient can afford their prescription medication and thus do nothing &lt;em&gt;OR&lt;/em&gt; you may advocate for your patient and for a better healthcare system by ensuring they get their medications and letting healthcare administrators know about this gap in ability to provide care. Which type of physician will you be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a Canadian medical student’s training, we become competent in the Can MEDs roles, all 7 of them. One of those roles is that of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.deptmedicine.utoronto.ca/CanMEDS/Health_Advocate.htm&quot;&gt;the Health Advocate&lt;/a&gt;. How does medical education and a future physician’s general experience in healthcare teach them to be an advocate and prepare them for contributing to making healthcare better meet patient needs? How do we ensure all “physicians [know their] responsibility [to] use their expertise and influence to advance the health and well-being of individual patients, communities, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.royalcollege.ca/portal/page/portal/rc/canmeds/framework&quot;&gt;populations.&lt;/a&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well first let me say I think advocates often come from deeply rooted values in justice and equality, but given that, becoming a health advocate can still be a result of teachings or lessons that solidfy this role in a future physician. Altogether, a culture in medicine around advocacy is needed to ensure fair, equitable and accessible care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Formalizing advocacy work in our education provides a consistent experience. At U of T in pre-clerkship training this consists of lectures on Canada’s healthcare system, examples of physician advocacy and the values of healthcare delivery. Often though, further depth in this requires your own initiative. In some cases, other medical schools provide more opportunities for those wishing to seek it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Boston University, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bu.edu/today/2013/training-med-students-to-become-patient-advocates/&quot;&gt;the lack of advocacy training&lt;/a&gt; was identified and a program developed to address this gap. Their four-year program helps develop its medical students into proficient health advocates by providing a longitudinal experience combining didactic sessions, mentorship and completion of a self-initiated project. The program typically sees 15% of a class enrol, begins with general theory on the social determinants of health, and then advances into applied experiences of advocacy. Students give back to the program by teaching sessions after they have mastered the content. I believe a program like this helps foster a culture in medicine of physician advocates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other means of developing a culture of advocacy in medicine include building leadership around students who are already involved in advocacy work. The University of Toronto has the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.md.utoronto.ca/program/leadership/LEAD.htm&quot;&gt;LEAD program&lt;/a&gt; which partially does this. Toronto and other medical schools also often have an active student body involved in their own advocacy work. At Toronto this spans from refugee health to sun safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Efforts to foster inter-professional education also serve to advance the health advocate role. Other health professionals are great advocates for their patients, including nurses and social workers. This, I hope, rubs off positively on physician trainees. It does on me, for example when the Canadian Federation for Medical Students this year advocated for a universal pharmacare strategy in Canada, it was largely backed by a &lt;a href=&quot;https://nursesunions.ca/sites/default/files/pharmacare_report.pdf&quot;&gt;policy&lt;/a&gt; report from the Canadian Federation of Nurses Unions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physician leaders in the public also play a key role by setting an example. Whether it is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theglobeandmail.com/globe-debate/why-canada-needs-a-national-pharmacare-program/article21086014/&quot;&gt;the Minister of Health and Long-term Care in Ontario advocating for Pharmacare&lt;/a&gt; or Physicians standing up for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theglobeandmail.com/globe-debate/dont-limit-the-role-of-health-officers-to-needles-and-pills/article21648693/&quot;&gt;patient’s needs outside of prescription drugs and hospital care&lt;/a&gt;. They all &lt;a href=&quot;http://healthydebate.ca/opinions/doctors-must-advocates&quot;&gt;inspire us students&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As healthcare transformation progresses in Canada, we will need more physicians who are willing to take on roles as health advocates for individual patients and communities to ensure the best health outcomes for all. Thankfully, within the CanMeds framework, we can establish educational milestones, learn from our peers, colleagues and mentors, and develop as advocates through our own experiential learning. Ultimately, I hope Canada’s future physicians continue to foster a culture of advocacy for the patients and communities they serve.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Datakind&#58; doing good data science</title>
   <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2014/11/09/dataoath/"/>
   <updated>2014-11-09T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2014/11/09/dataoath</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.DataKind.org&quot;&gt;DataKind&lt;/a&gt;, an organization that I have been following for some time, held a session exploring the need for a ‘hippocratic oath [in] data science’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As research using massive amounts of data becomes more and more popular, there develops a need for an ethical line. Similar to physician’s ‘do no harm’ mantra and the intimate access they have to a person’s experience with health, the data scientists access to large swaths of data from distributed sources has the potential for harm and exposure of personal information. To begin a discussion on defining this ethical line and come up with a ‘hippocratic oath for data science’ the people at DataKind held &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.datakind.org/blog/meetup-recap-untangling-ethical-questions-in-data-science/&quot;&gt;an evening forum&lt;/a&gt;. It has left me with many thoughts on this, especially as data science becomes pervasive in all aspects of our lives (including our health), and I felt compelled to share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;From DataKind.org:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;message&quot;&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;The Hippocratic Oath for Data Science&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tim Rich closed the discussion beautifully with a call to action for us all: “My big beef with discussions on ethics is it ends at the door.  Because we are all engaged in data science as our trade, writing down ethical statements is what needs to happen next.  We can talk all day long but we need to start codifying and we need to work together by writing it down.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;While we almost certainly ended the evening with more questions than before, everyone at least left with more insight into the ethical challenges at play in our work.  For further reading, Jake recommends the book, &lt;a href=&quot;http://books.google.com/books/about/Raw_Data_Is_an_Oxymoron.html?id=oARaHF4D6h0C&quot;&gt;Raw Data is an Oxymoron&lt;/a&gt;, and we also love the &lt;a href=&quot;https://responsibledata.io/&quot;&gt;Responsible Data Forum series&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.datasociety.net/&quot;&gt;Data &amp;amp; Society&lt;/a&gt; as well as &lt;a href=&quot;http://dssg.io/blog/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Data Science for Social Good fellows blog series&lt;/a&gt; for more stories from the forefront of data-for-good!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some food for thought. Let me know what you think.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Healthcare Triage and different healthcare systems</title>
   <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2014/08/22/healthcaretraigesystemsvideos/"/>
   <updated>2014-08-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2014/08/22/healthcaretraigesystemsvideos</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Delivery of healthcare differs vastly across nations. We, in Canada, often contrast our system with that of the United States. However, frequently the facts of the system give way to myths. So perhaps a little evidence-based clarification is in order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I watch &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCabaQPYxxKepWUsEVQMT4Kw&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Healthcare Triage&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which is a youtube channel run by Dr. Aaron Carroll. He is a &lt;a href=&quot;http://pediatrics.iu.edu/chsr/our-team/faculty/bio-carroll/&quot;&gt;pediatrician&lt;/a&gt; at Indiana University and blogs at &lt;a href=&quot;http://theincidentaleconomist.com/&quot;&gt;the Incidental Economist&lt;/a&gt;. Recently, him and his collaborators put together a series on several healthcare systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their series is especially great because it discusses several healthcare systems one after another with clear discriptions for each system (and sometimes what the country’s citizens think of their system). Whether you are in medicine, interested in medicine or someone who may need some medicine (read: healthcare) I recommend watching this series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video Canadians should watch first:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/1TPr3h-UDA0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I really learnt from the series was how different the various systems of healthcare are across the countries discussed. Most people are aware of the United States system design and perhaps how it differs from their home country. However, I hadn’t realized before how different England and Canada were from each other. Or that France constantly changed their system but universally love it. Or that England is so cost effective with minimal out of pocket costs to the patient and is (nearly) truly a socialized system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;international-health-care-systems-playlist&quot;&gt;International Health Care Systems playlist&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole playlist &lt;em&gt;currently&lt;/em&gt; includes: The United States, &lt;strong&gt;Canada&lt;/strong&gt;, France, England, Singapore, Germay and Switzerland. More may be added in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/videoseries?list=PLkfBg8ML-gIngk82SUbTp6Og_KkYfJ6oF&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Using Jekyll, Poole and Lanyon to setup my github user page</title>
   <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2014/08/04/lanyonsetup/"/>
   <updated>2014-08-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2014/08/04/lanyonsetup</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;Github pages&lt;/a&gt; is where I learnt github repositories could be used to host a website using &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;jekyll&lt;/a&gt;. This website was created using the theme &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/poole/lanyon&quot;&gt;lanyon&lt;/a&gt;, which derives from &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/poole/poole&quot;&gt;poole&lt;/a&gt;. Jekyll, Poole and Lanyon are all characters from &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strange_Case_of_Dr_Jekyll_and_Mr_Hyde&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Strange Case of Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;general-custimizations&quot;&gt;General custimizations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added Disqus comments using &lt;a href=&quot;http://joshualande.com/jekyll-github-pages-poole/&quot;&gt;Joshua Lande’s guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added Google analytics using &lt;a href=&quot;http://joshualande.com/jekyll-github-pages-poole/&quot;&gt;the same guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added SEO streamlining from &lt;a href=&quot;http://jethrokuan.github.io/2013/12/20/SEO-with-Jekyll.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added CNAME from &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/articles/tips-for-configuring-a-cname-record-with-your-dns-provider&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added a favicon (mouse brain with the cerebellum coloured - posterior-lateral view)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added tags page&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added archive page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;css-and-headhtml-modifcations&quot;&gt;CSS and head.html modifcations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added the font-awesome css in head.html and then used its icons to display my social media presence in the sidebar. 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://fortawesome.github.io/Font-Awesome/examples/&quot;&gt;Future resource for help with font-awesome&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sidebar-modifications&quot;&gt;Sidebar modifications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added my gravatar to the sidebar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Added social links with _config.yml settings I set-up and font-awesome icons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My repository can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/psteadman/psteadman.github.io&quot;&gt;https://github.com/psteadman/psteadman.github.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;things-id-like-to-explore&quot;&gt;Things I’d like to explore&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Medium and their website - &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;https://medium.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://johnmacfarlane.net/pandoc/&quot;&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jgm/pandoc&quot;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HTML and CSS&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getbootstrap.com/&quot;&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; - from Mark Otto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ideas&quot;&gt;Ideas&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Code a bar below current header with most popular tags (count beside) and serve as link to view all posts with that tag&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The MD/PhD program at UofT</title>
   <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2014/07/30/mdphd-UofT/"/>
   <updated>2014-07-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2014/07/30/mdphd-UofT</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mdphd.utoronto.ca/&quot;&gt;The MD/PhD program&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Toronto is the largest of its kind in Canada. My class, starting in 2013, had 11 students in it. The program is run out of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.medicine.utoronto.ca/&quot;&gt;Faculty of Medicine&lt;/a&gt; and as the name states is split into two sections: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.md.utoronto.ca/&quot;&gt;MD side&lt;/a&gt; and the PhD side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most students complete MD year 1 and then transition to the PhD phase. An alternative avenue is to stay for MD year 2 and transition to the PhD phase afterwards. Following the successful defense of the PhD, the final 3 years of the MD degree are completed. Total time is (hopefully) 8 years, though this varies. The choice of PhD department and supervisor is done during first year of medicine with significant freedom to choose from the majority of departments at the university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current curriculum, as noted above, separates the two degrees. However, since we really should be learning to combine our clinical and research skills, some degree of integration should exist. The program is working on improving integration, as discussed in a 2012 report (Unfortunately no longer on-line).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions on my experiences with the program, easiest means to contact me is &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pesteadman&quot;&gt;@pesteadman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;university-of-toronto&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.utoronto.ca&quot;&gt;University of Toronto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2013-Present&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Doctor of Medicine &lt;br /&gt;
Faculty of Medicine&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2014-Present&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Doctor of Philosophy &lt;br /&gt;
Institute of Medical Science &lt;br /&gt;
Supervisor: Dr. Paul Frankland&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.medicine.utoronto.ca/&quot;&gt;Faculty of Medicine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.md.utoronto.ca/&quot;&gt;MD program&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mdphd.utoronto.ca/&quot;&gt;MD/PhD program&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ims.utoronto.ca/&quot;&gt;Institute of Medical Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jflab.ca&quot;&gt;Paul Frankland’s lab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>MSc at University of Toronto</title>
   <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2014/07/29/msc/"/>
   <updated>2014-07-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2014/07/29/msc</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;university-of-toronto&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.utoronto.ca&quot;&gt;University of Toronto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2011-2013&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Master of Science – Collaborative Program in Neuroscience &lt;br /&gt;
Department of Medical Biophysics &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The influence of autism-associated genes on the mouse cerebellum, assessed using a magnetic resonance imaging atlas&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Supervisor: Dr. Jason Lerch&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;courses&quot;&gt;Courses&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neuroanatomy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advanced Medical Imaging&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optical, Thermal and Radiation Biophysics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clinical Imaging for Physical Scientists&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Biophysics Seminar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thesis was a bit rushed as I was late deciding between going on to my PhD or graduating to pursue MD or MD/PhD studies. Ultimately the letter of acceptance made the decision for me. My thesis can be found in &lt;a href=&quot;https://tspace.library.utoronto.ca/bitstream/1807/42923/6/Steadman_Patrick_E_201311_MSc_thesis.pdf&quot;&gt;t-space&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was fortunate to join a great &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mouseimaging.ca&quot;&gt;lab&lt;/a&gt; and work on some amazing projects. The first project I was a part of a study on how memory formation results in structural changes in the brain. The second project aimed to understand whether mutations in specific genes that have been associated with Autism Spectrum Disorders alter brain morphology and to what extent they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Publications from my MSc:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steadman, P. E.&lt;/strong&gt;, Ellegood, J., Szulc, K. U., Turnbull, D. H., Joyner, A. L., Henkelman, R. M. and Lerch, J. P. (2014). Genetic effects on Cerebellar structure across mouse models of Autism using a magnetic resonance imaging atlas. Autism Research. doi:&lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/aur.1344&quot;&gt;10.1002/aur.1344&lt;/a&gt;. - &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfari.org/news-and-opinion/toolbox/2013/map-of-cerebellum-highlights-diversity-in-autism-mice&quot;&gt;SFARI news write-up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ellegood, J., Markx, S., Lerch, J. P., &lt;strong&gt;Steadman, P. E.&lt;/strong&gt;, Kushner, S. A., Henkelman, R. M., Karayiorgou, M., and Gogos, J. A. (2014). Recapitulation of Human Neuroanatomical Phenotypes in a Mouse Model of the 22q11.2 Microdeletion. Molecular Psychiatry. doi:&lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/mp.2013.112&quot;&gt;10.1038/mp.2013.112&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chakravarty, M. M., &lt;strong&gt;Steadman, P.&lt;/strong&gt;, van Eede, M. C., Calcott, R. D., Gu, V., Shaw, P., Raznahan, A., Louis, C. D., Lerch, J. P. (2013). Performing label-fusion-based segmentation using multiple automatically generated templates. Human brain mapping. doi:&lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/hbm.22092&quot;&gt;10.1002/hbm.22092&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>BSc at McMaster University</title>
   <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2014/07/28/bsc/"/>
   <updated>2014-07-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2014/07/28/bsc</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;mcmaster-university&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mcmaster.ca&quot;&gt;McMaster University&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2006-2011&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Bachelor of Science (Honours) – Summa cum laude &lt;br /&gt;
Major: &lt;em&gt;Medical and Health Physics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;12 Months of Co-op work at Health Canada and The Hospital for Sick Children&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;selected-list-of-courses&quot;&gt;Selected list of courses:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A detailed description of my undergraduate program doesn’t exist anymore. This may be from funding cutbacks since my program typically struggled to attract enough students. For some reason the sound of Medical Physics just wasn’t too appealing… So I have listed the courses I took after first year. The top three sections are courses required of the Medical and Health Physics curriculum (minus 1 or 2 electives in the Biological Sciences).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;medical-physics&quot;&gt;Medical Physics&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advanced Medical Imaging&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optical, Thermal and Radiation Biophysics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clinical Imaging for Physical Scientists&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Biophysics Seminar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Computational Medical Physics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Physics in Medicine (Overview of medical imaging)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Biophotonics, Introduction to&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Radiation and Radioisotope Methodology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Radiation Biology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Radioactivity and Radiation Interactions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;mathematics-and-physics&quot;&gt;Mathematics and Physics&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Digital Logic and Computer Systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nuclear Physics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Statistical Methods for Scientists&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mathematical Physics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quantum Mechanics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Physical Optics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mathematical Modelling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Differential Equations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vector Calculus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electricity and Magnetism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Modern Physics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Classical Mechanics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thermodynamics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;biological-sciences&quot;&gt;Biological Sciences&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clinical Biochemistry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neurobiology of Memory and Learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cell Biology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Human Biology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Proteins and Nucleic Acids&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Organic Chemistry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;social-sciences-and-humanities&quot;&gt;Social Sciences and Humanities&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anthropology of Healing, Health and Illness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contemporary Canadian Fiction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mental Health&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Canadian Adolescents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Microeconomics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The key to early diagnosis in Autism&#58; three research areas</title>
   <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2014/02/17/ASD-research-short/"/>
   <updated>2014-02-17T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2014/02/17/ASD-research-short</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I’m hoping they will realize they get better bang for their buck, the earlier intervention is given.”&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a title=&quot;Toronto Star February 2013&quot; href=&quot;http://www.thestar.com/news/canada/2013/02/08/ontarios_auditor_general_to_review_autism_services.html&quot;&gt;said Simone Papernick of Whitby&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ontario Auditor General just initiated a review of Autism Services to better determine how to spend the recently tripled budget for treatment. The budget now stands at $186 million a year for Ontarian’s with the developmental disorder. Demand has never been higher, Autism is now estimated to affect 1 in 88 children, based on reports from the Centre For Disease Control in the United States. However, one of the best solutions to making treatment more effective is earlier diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diagnosing children at an earlier age means earlier intervention at a time when the child’s brain is changing rapidly and has the potential to be influenced by life experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently the best therapy for young children with Autism is Intensive Behavioural Intervention (IBI), which uses a comprehensive approach to support a child’s healthy development. This therapy costs as much as $60,000 a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To improve the effectiveness of IBI, three early interventions hold strong potential. The first is the understanding of genetic factors which contribute to increased risk in developing Autism. The second is understanding how children who go on to develop autism have subtle differences in behaviour from children who don’t develop the disorder. Thirdly, using imaging brain during development to understand how the brain may grow differently in children who go on to be diagnosed with Autism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to seeing all three grow over time and tell us more about the brain’s intricacies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further information:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The Hospital for Sick Children's Stephen Scherer on TVO's the agenda: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tbUFMf2hHKU&quot;&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tbUFMf2hHKU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The genetic landscapes of autism spectrum disorders by Huguet G, Ey E, Bourgeron T. (2013) - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23875794&quot;&gt;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23875794&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A Comparison of Neuroimaging Findings in Childhood Onset Schizophrenia and Autism Spectrum Disorder: A Review of the Literature by Baribeau DA, Anagnostou E. (2013) - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24391605&quot;&gt;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24391605&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Translational approaches to the biology of Autism: false dawn or a new era? by Ecker C, Spooren W, Murphy DG. (2013) - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22801412&quot;&gt;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22801412&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Baby Sib study - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.autismspeaks.org/science/research-initiatives/high-risk-baby-sibs&quot;&gt;http://www.autismspeaks.org/science/research-initiatives/high-risk-baby-sibs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Autism research, traversing the full spectrum to help children</title>
   <link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2013/01/19/autism-oped/"/>
   <updated>2013-01-19T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2013/01/19/autism-oped</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With a prevalence of one in 88 children, autism has moved to the forefront of discussions amongst Canadian parents. To propel this discussion from the kitchen table to the greater community, the Toronto Star produced a useful series entitled the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thestar.com/news/world/autismproject&quot; title=&quot;Autism Project&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Autism Project&lt;/a&gt;. Yet, little has been discussed on how research is describing brain dysfunction in autism and developing treatments to correct this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To recap first: autism, as medicine currently defines it, is a disorder where the brain’s processing of information is affected, disrupting communication, sociability and other behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Star’s series examined the personal experience of autism from the perspectives of a parent and individuals with the disorder. It highlighted new behavioural therapies, the work being done to study the genetics of autism patients, and the frustrating wait many parents face in getting their child access to behavioural interventions. However, the series missed how research on the biology of autism is translating our knowledge of genetics into new treatments. This matters because this research contains the potential to improve lives and lessen autism’s impact on society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The brain in autism processes information differently and understanding the details of the process will help facilitate research on new treatments. The federal government recognizes this and has just committed $1-million to funding a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cihr-irsc.gc.ca/e/46009.html&quot; title=&quot;CIHR announcement&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Canadian research chair&lt;/a&gt; for 5 years to accelerate Canada’s contribution to finding new treatments. This represents a good start to advancing Canadian research on autism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canada’s science contribution is accelerating as well. Researchers, as part of an international project, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ontariogenomics.ca/research/project/44&quot; title=&quot;Scherer Screening&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;screened over 6000 people with autism&lt;/a&gt; to understand the disorder’s genetic factors. This and other work showed that many genetic pieces contribute to the scientific puzzle of autism. Using these genetic factors, a careful examination of the brain’s biological dysfunction in autism can be done to develop new treatments. This includes unraveling changes in brain function, development and structure associated with each genetic piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small success story has come with a specific gene that causes Fragile X syndrome, a disorder closely related to autism. Researchers first laid a foundation for developing treatments by characterizing the Fragile X gene’s effect on brain function and structure. Then, earlier this year, a team at Massachusetts Institute of Technology used this knowledge to &lt;a href=&quot;http://stm.sciencemag.org/content/4/152/152ra128.abstract&quot; title=&quot;FXS Reversal&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;reverse the syndrome’s deficits&lt;/a&gt;. They corrected brain abnormalities in a model of Fragile X syndrome and &lt;a href=&quot;http://stm.sciencemag.org/content/4/152/152ra127&quot; title=&quot;FXS phase 2 trial article&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;improved social engagement in Fragile X patients&lt;/a&gt;, all with the same treatment. This case illustrates why establishing new treatments through an understanding of the brain in autism matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fragile X story is just one piece of the puzzle and many more pieces contribute to autism. To continue progress, knowledge on how genetics change brain function and structure in autism must press on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, almost every month this body of knowledge grows. Since 2011 several models of genetic traits in autism have had biological and behaviour problems reversed using targeted treatments. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed?term=Autism-related%20deficits%20via%20dysregulated%20eIF4E-dependent%20translational%20control&quot; title=&quot;McGill Autism&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this month researchers at McGill University&lt;/a&gt; announced successful correction of behaviour and biological shortfalls in a new genetic model of autism. Though this work is not ready for humans, it does strengthen the foundation on what exactly is going awry in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These frequent advances help build an understanding of the biological pathways affected in autism and some successful ways to therapeutically target the brain for treating the disorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the mountain to climb in autism research remains high, great gains have been made. We now know that the genetic contribution to autism is strong and that many different genetic factors cause the disorder. Discussions on autism now must include new research focused on deciphering the disorder’s biological riddle. Solving this enables science to translate its genetic knowledge to better treatments for individuals with autism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going forward, the key to further success will be translating the genetic factors to treatments that improve the lives of children and adults with autism. Furthermore, more genetic models will need to be investigated to form a comprehensive picture of autism and in deciding which targeted treatments to use. Only further support from the government and public in funding autism research can empower scientists to answer these remaining questions.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>